"How to Prevent Wrinkles with Diet"
"Skin Wrinkling:
Can Food Make a Difference?"
Population studies
have found that healthy diets
tend to be associated
with less severe facial aging.
Presumably this is
because unhealthy foods
might increase
the oxidative stress load,
be pro-inflammatory,
and the advanced glycation
end products
I talk about in my video
The Best Diet for Healthy Aging,
whereas healthy foods
might provide protection
by having an inside-out
sunscreen effect,
stimulating collagen production
and DNA repair,
which could help explain why
a meat and junk predominant
eating pattern
was associated
with more wrinkles,
whereas a fruit-dominant pattern
or those eating more fruits,
vegetables,
and nuts
may enjoy less wrinkling.
Vegetables, beans,
and olive oil
appeared protective
versus meat and dairy.
Fish was initially correlated
with less skin wrinkling,
but the association disappeared
upon multiple
regression analyses,
meaning it was likely
a spurious result
due to fish consumption being
associated with, for example,
other healthy foods such as
salad or cooked vegetables.
Higher vitamin C intakes
were associated
with lower odds
of a wrinkled appearance
in a study of 4,000
middle-aged American women.
In terms of specific foods,
yellow and green vegetables
may be particularly protective.
The Daniell scale
was used to test the effect
of crow's feet wrinkles
around the eyes
of seven hundred women.
Those eating
less than one daily serving
of green or yellow veggies
averaged about a three
on the Daniell scale,
while women eating
more than two servings a day
averaged closer to a two.
But maybe people
who go out of their way
to eat more vegetables,
also go out of their way
to wear more sunblock.
Or maybe people
who eat more meat
are out barbequing
in the sun.
Researchers suggest,
"Global disease
prevention strategies
might benefit from emphasizing
that a healthy diet
is also linked
to less facial wrinkling,"
but first we should make sure
to establish cause-and-effect.
In my video How to Naturally
Reduce Wrinkles with Food,
I cover interventional studies
showing that two palmfuls
of almonds a day
can both increase
the UV resistance
of people's skin
and decrease wrinkle severity
and width compared to those,
instead,
randomized to nut-free snacks.
What other foods have been shown
to counter skin aging?
The amount of flaxseed oil found
in a daily 3/4 of a tablespoon
(11.25 g) of ground flaxseeds
significantly increased
skin smoothness
compared to placebo
within six weeks.
In vitro, sulforaphane,
the cruciferous compound
in broccoli,
is able to mitigate
the premature skin aging
induced by air pollution
particulate matter in vitro,
but it has not been
put to the test.
But a component of soy foods
has been tested.
Postmenopausal women
were given four servings a day
of soy foods worth
of isoflavones for six months.
Unfortunately,
there was no control group,
but they did take skin biopsies
from their butts
before and after
and found
a significant improvement
in skin thickness,
along with increased
collagen content
and elastic fibers.
How about
a randomized controlled trial
with a more modest soy intake?
About a serving and a half a day
of soy's worth of isoflavones
was pitted against placebo
in middle-aged women.
Facial skin elasticity
improved by week 8,
and an improvement
in fine wrinkles
was noted by week 12.
Another 12-week study
using equol directly,
which is a compound
that good gut bacteria
can turn soy isoflavones into,
found a significant reduction
in wrinkle depth,
though you have to have
the right gut bugs.
See my video How to Convert
Into an Equol Producer.
The only other interventional
food study on wrinkles
I could find tested one
of my favorite fruits: mangoes.
Feeding mango to mice reduced
UV-induced wrinkle formation,
but it wasn't put to the test
in people until 2020.
Light-skinned
postmenopausal women
were randomized to eat
about a half cup (120 ml)
of champagne mango or around
a cup and a half (360 ml)
every day for 16 weeks.
Lucky ducks!
Unfortunately,
as an exploratory study,
there was no usual
diet control group,
but compared to baseline,
the deep-wrinkle severity
in the half-cup group
significantly decreased
by week eight and remained so
for the duration of the study.
In contrast, to the funding
National Mango Board's chagrin,
average wrinkle severity
got worse
by the end of the 16 weeks
in the cup and a half group.
The researchers suggested
it might have been due
to the extra sugar intake,
but there wasn't
actually any changes
in blood sugar levels,
so it remains a mystery.
The paucity
of interventional trials
limits the confidence one
can put into recommendations,
but the best approximation
for an anti-wrinkle diet
would be one naturally rich
in antioxidants,
anti-inflammatory,
and would limit sugar spikes
and glycation
both by limiting added sugars
and refined carbs,
and avoiding preformed
advanced glycation end products
found in fried,
grilled, and broiled meats.
In other words, when patients
inquire about a diet
that might contribute
to younger-looking skin,
evidence supports
the recommendation
to follow a whole foods,
plant-based diet.